[{"question":"Bhopal gas accident occurred in which year due to which gas?","a":"(a) 1986/Methyl  isocynate","b":"(c) 1984/Methyl isocynate  ","c":"(c) 1985/CO","d":"(d) 1985/Ethyl isocynate","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Photochemical smog does not include:","a":"(a) PAN","b":"(b) NO","c":"(c) CO","d":"d) O","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"DDT causes egg shell thinning in birds becauseit inhibits:","a":"(a) calmodulin","b":"(b) calcium ATPase","c":"(c) magnesium ATPase","d":"(d) carbonic anhydrase","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Ozone layer in stratosphere is effected by:","a":"(a) Excess CO₂","b":"b) Excess CO","c":"c) Chloro-fluoro-caroon","d":"(d) Low rainfall","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"6. Why is the concentration of ozone less over thenorth and south poles?","a":"(a) CFCs accumulate only in area where the  air is cold ","b":"(b) CFC use is highest in these areas","c":"c) CFCs stick to frozen water vapour and able to act catalysts","d":"d) UV rays are stronger in the atmosphere","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"7. The percentage of air pollution caused due tosmoke is","a":"(a) 10-15%","b":"b) 15-20%","c":"(c) 20-25%","d":"d) 2-5%","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Increase in productivity most likely cause lossof species because:","a":"a) those species that increase in productivity outcompete other species. ","b":"(b) the causes of increased productivity in onespecies do not necessarily have the same effect in all species.  ","c":" (c) there are inadequate resources available  for productivity increases in all species.","d":"(d) all of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The maximum biological magnification of  DDT through food web is seen in:","a":"(a) Algae","b":"(b) Bacteria","c":"(c) Higher plants","d":"d) Man","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In case CO₂ of earth's atmosphere disappears, the temperature of earth's surface would:","a":"(a) Increase","b":"(b) Decrease","c":"c) Depend on oxygen concentration","d":"d) Remain the same","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Pollution of SO  , destroys:","a":"(a) Fungi","b":"b)  Lichen","c":"(c) Algae","d":"d) Fishes","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which organisms in a food chain consisting  of algae, copepods (small crustaceans), small fish, large fish, and ospreys (fish-eating birds of  prey) would have the highest concentrations ofDDT in their tissues","a":"(a) Algae","b":"b) Copepods","c":"(c) Small  fish","d":"(d) Ospreys","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Major aerosol pollutant in jet emission   is:","a":"a) Sulphur dioxide","b":"(b) Carbon monoxide","c":"(c) Methane","d":"d) Fluorocarbon","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Pollution indicator plants:","a":"(a) are resistant to pollution","b":"b) can purify the atmosphere","c":"(c) are very sensitive to pollutants","d":"(d) can indicate onset of rains","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Noise pollution is created if noise is in excess to:","a":"a) 70-75 dB","b":"(b) 50-60 dB","c":"(c) 80-99 dB","d":"(d) 40-65 dB","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Maintenance of forests in areas with increasing carbon dioxide levels is critical because:","a":"(a) forests can serve as carbon dioxide sinks by  increasing photosynthesis. ","b":"(b) the use of carbon dioxide by trees reduces carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.  ","c":"(c) forests are needed to reduce global warming","d":"d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Effect of pollution is first marked on:","a":"a) Micro-organisms","b":"(b) Green vegetation of an area","c":"(c) Food crop","d":"d) Mammals","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The Montreal Protocol refers to:","a":"a) persistent organic pollutants","b":"(b) global warming and climate change","c":"(c) substances that deplete the ozone layer","d":"(d) biosafety of genetically modified organisms","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which is a non-degradable pollutant?","a":"(a) Smoke","b":"(b) Polythene","c":"(c) Copper scraps","d":"d) Iron scraps","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following is not used for disinfectionof drinking water?","a":"(a) Chlorine","b":"(b) Ozone","c":"c) Chloramine","d":"d) Phenyl","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the followig is not a major contributor  to the current global increase in methane level?","a":"a) Activity of serobic bacteria in rice paddies","b":"(b) Burning of tropical biomass","c":"c) Flatulence of herbivorous ruminants","d":"d) Decomposition of waste in landfill dumps","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following statement (s) is/are  correct about noise pollution? ","a":"(a) It is an undesired high level of sound.","b":"(b) It is measured in dB.","c":"(e) It can cause damage to heart, increase  blood  cholesterol and even raise blood pressure","d":"d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"EcoSan' toilets, being used in Kerala and  Srilanka are hygienic and cost effective solution  to human waste disposal. Mark the correct  statement regarding EcoSan. ","a":"(a) Recycled human waste from this can be","b":"b) They are called composting toilets.","c":"c) They do not depend on water for the disposal of excreta.","d":"d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Identify correct statement and choose the option.","a":"(a) The major contribution in green house gases is of CH.  ","b":"(b) Global warming is because of ozone depletion. ","c":"(c) When organic waste enters into a water  body its BOD increases.","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"29. Consider the following statements. Choose the  correct option. ","a":"(1) By the end of twentieth century, the forest  cover in India was reduced to 19.4 percent.","b":"ii) National Forest Policy was iplemented in the year 1988.  ","c":"(iii) The average annual production of drygrass or hay in India is about 250 million  tons.  ","d":"(iv) About 10% of the world's population lives","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Frequent occurrence of water blooms in a lake indicates:","a":"(a) Nutrient deficiency.","b":"b) Oxygen deficiency","c":"c) Excessive nutrient availability","d":"d) Absence of herbivores in the lake","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"In cities like Mumbai and Kolkata the major air pollutants are:","a":"(a) Ozone","b":"(b) CO and oxides of sulphur","c":"e) Hydrocarbons and hot air","d":"(d) Algal spores and marsh gas","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Thermal pollution of water bodies is due to:","a":"a) Discharge of heat (hot water) from power plants","b":"(b) Discharge of chemicals from industries.","c":"(c) Discharge of waste from mining.","d":"d) Discharge of agricultural run off.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Gaseous pollutants can be controlled by:","a":"(a) Arrestors","b":"b) Electrostatic precipitators","c":"(c) Pyrolysis","d":"(d) Adsorption","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which pollutant is absent in automobile exhausts?","a":"a) SO,","b":"(b) Fly ash","c":"(c) Hydrocarbon gases","d":"(d) Nitrogen oxides","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"35.  It is said, the Taj Mahal may be destroyed  due to:","a":"(a) food in Yamuna river.","b":"b) decomposition of marble as a result of high temperature","c":"(c) air pollutants released from oil refinery of mathura","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Mark the statement that describes the eco-  friendly disposal of municipal solid- waste. ","a":"(a) It should be burnt to completion.  ","b":"(b) It should be dumped in open waste land.","c":"(c) It should be dumped in sanitary landfills.  ","d":"(d) It should be sorted out into bio-degradable,","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following  does not cause pollution?","a":"a) Thermal power project","b":"(b) Steel power plant","c":"c) Automobiles","d":"(d) Hydro electric project","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The enrichment of water by nutrients is","a":"a) Mineralization","b":"b) Biomagnification","c":"(c) Eutrophication","d":"(d) All of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Non-point source of water pollution is","a":" (a) Sewage outlet","b":"(b) Effluents from a factory","c":"(c) Agricultural runoff","d":"(d) All of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Photochemical smog always contains:","a":"a) Aluminum ions","b":"b) Methane","c":"(c) Ozone","d":"d) Phosphorus","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Lichens are important in the studies atmosphere pollution because they ","a":"(a) can grow in polluted atmosphere","b":"(b) can readily multiply in polluted atmosphere","c":"(c) efficiently purify the atmosphere","d":"(d) are very sensitive to pollutants like sulphur dioxide","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Carbon monoxide (CO) is harmful to man because","a":"(a) It forms carbolic acid.","b":"(b) It generates excess CO₂","c":"(c) It is carcinogenic","d":"d) It competes with O  , for haemoglobin.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The greatest air pollution disaster during recentyears had been witnessed in: ","a":"(a) Kolkata","b":"(b)Ahmedabad","c":"c) Agra","d":"(d) Bhopal","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Sonic booms\" refer to:","a":"(a) Shock waves","b":"b) Noise of traffic","c":"c) Noise of siren","d":"(d) Nitrates","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which one has the least green house effect?","a":"(a) carbon dioxide","b":"(b) nitrogen gas","c":"(c) water vapour","d":"(d) ozone","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"","a":"","b":"","c":"","d":"","hint":"","correct":"b"}]